Finding Aid for Rudolph H. Gjelsness papers, circa 1919-1968
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Rudolph H. Gjelsness papers
circa 1919-1968
Gjelsness, Rudolph H. (Rudolph Hjalmar), 1894-1968.
851310 Aa 2
Correspondence and other papers relating to his work with the American Library Association's Committee on Revision of the Anglo-American Cataloging Rules, 1935-1941; letters from his former students upon the occasion of his retirement in 1964; personal correspondence, including letters to his parents from relatives in Norway, 1880-1935 and letters written while in service during World War I; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
7 linear feet
Donor No. 4809.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Rudolph Hjalmar Gjelsness (1894-1968), librarian and library educator, was born October 18, 1894 in Reynolds, North Dakota. His Norwegian-born parents, Marius S. and Karoline O. Gjelsness, had settled on a farm in that community when it was part of the Dakota Territory. As a child, he learned to speak and write Norwegian in his home. He attended the University of North Dakota, from which he graduated in 1916 with an A.B. degree in Zoology, and a teaching certificate. In 1916-1917, he was high school principal in Adams North Dakota, and in the fall of 1917 he entered the University or Illinois Library School.
His library studies were interrupted by World War I; from 1917-1919 he served in the U.S. Air Force 5th Company, 3rd Regiment, American Expeditionary Forces, with assignments in the United States, France and Germany. In March of 1919, while still in France, he was discharged from the Air Force in order to work under the auspices of the American Library Association as reference librarian at the AFF University at Beaume, France.
On return rig to the United States in September 1,919, he resumed his library studies and obtained the Bachelor of Library Science degree from the University of Illinois in 1920. In 1930, he married Ruth Weaver in New York City. They had two children, Elizabeth (Mrs. Donelson E. Dulany, Jr.) and Barent.
Gjelsness began his professional library career in 1920 as Head of the Order Department at the University of Oregon Library, where he remained until 1922. In the next ten years he progressed to exceedingly more responsible positions at the University of California at Berkeley, the University of Michigan, and the New York Public Library, always engaging in some aspect of ordering or cataloging work.
Progress in his library career was interrupted in 1924-25 by a stimulating year at the University of Oslo, Norway, studying Norwegian Literature as a Fellow of the American-Scandinavian Foundation. There he developed a strong interest, in several contemporary Norwegian writers and translated works of Björnsterne Björnson, Johan Ludvig Herberg, Olaf Dunn and Johann Falkberget. For several years after his return from Norway he corresponded with Falkberget, and in 1930, W.W. Norton Published Gjelsness' translation of Falkberget's Lisbeth of Jarnfjeld.
From 1932-37, he was Librarian and Professor at the University of Arizona, which he left to become Professor of Library Science at the University of Michigan and later Head of the Department of Library Science, remaining in that position until his retirement in 1964. He then returned to the University of Arizona Library as Chief of the Special Collections Division, a post he was occupying at the time of his accidental death on August 16, 1968 while in San Juan, Puerto Rico on a special assignment.
At various times during his career he was on leave to carry out library projects in foreign countries, most notably in Mexico, where he was Director of the United States-sponsored Benjamin Franklin Library in Mexico City. He held positions on numerous committees of the American Library Association, the most significant of which was as Chairman of the Committee on Catalog Code Revision. The work of the Code Revision Committee resulted in the 1941 publication of ALA Catalog Rules, Author and Title Entries, with Gjelsness as Editor in Chief. He was the author of more than sixty articles in professional periodicals.
The bulk of the collection consists of Gjelsness' professional correspondence between 1930 and 1965; materials concerning the committees of the American Library Association on which he served, and relating to his foreign assignments; extensive files of drafts of the revision of the Catalog Code, together with related. correspondence; and comments on the final draft of the Code.
Some unusual items are letters in Norwegian written between 1881 and 1935 to Marius S. and Karoline O. Gjelsness, parents of Rudolph Gjelsness. The correspondents were family and friends in Norway, and residents of other Norwegian. communities in north-central United States. Business papers of Marius S. Gjelsness from 1885 to 1917 reflect his activities as a member of the local school board and as a leader in his church. Several catalogues of merchandise are included.
There are also early personal letters of Rudolph H. Gjelsness written to his mother and his sister Helen during the years he was in the army and later a student in Norway, as well as a few from his days as a library science student and a beginning librarian. There are also a few folders of his World War memorabilia.
Subjects:
American Library Association.; Michigan--Emigration and immigration.; Gjelsness, Rudolph H. (Rudolph Hjalmar), 1894-1968.; Libraries--United States.; Norway--Emigration and immigration.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Library Science.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; World War, 1914-1918.; Norwegian Americans--Michigan.; Immigrants--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Bishop, William Warner, 1871-1955.; Gjelsness family.; Photographs.; University of Michigan. Law Library.; University of Michigan. Library.; William L. Clements Library.
- Karoline O. and Marius S. Gjelsness
  - Correspondence (photocopies)
    - Undated, 4 folders (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
    - 1880 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1881 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1882 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - April 1883-March 1884 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - April-December 1884 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1885 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - January-June 1886 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - July-December 1886 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - January 1887 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - February-March 1887 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - April-June 1887 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - July-October 1887 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - November-December 1887 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - January-February 1888 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - March-June 1888 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - July-December 1888 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 1889-1891 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - January-May 1892 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - June 1892 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - July 1892 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - August-December 1892 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - 1895 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - 1896-1897 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - 1901-1902 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - 1914-1918 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - 1919-1935 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Marius S. Gjelsness
  - Miscellaneous papers
    - 1880-1884 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - 1885-1891 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - 1901-1902 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - 1903-1905 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - 1913-1914 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - 1915 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - 1916 (Box 1, Folder 37-38)
    - January-June 1917 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - July-December 1917 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Rudolph H. Gjelsness
  - Biographical data (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - Memorial statements (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - World War I
    - Correspondence
      - December 1917-March 1918 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - April-July 1918 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - August-December 1918 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - January-March 1919 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - April-August 1919 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 3 folders (Box 2, Folder 9-11)
  - Fellowship in Norway 12-123 (Box 2)
  - Personal correspondence, 1919-1923 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Professional papers
    - Correspondence
      - 1924-1925 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - 1926-1928 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - 1930-1931 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - 1936 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - 1940-1946 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - 1950-1954 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - 1955-1959 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - 1961-June 1964 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - July-December 1964 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - January-June 1965 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - July-December 1965 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - 1966 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - January-June 1967 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - July 1967-June 1968 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous papers
    - American Library Institute (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Carey, Matthew-Publishing (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Holme, Frank-Bandar Log Press (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Festschrift in honor of R.H. Gjelsness Books in America's Past (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Honorary Degree-Luther College (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Honorary Degree-University of North Dakota (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Michigan University Department of Library Science, Alumni Notes, May 1948 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - References, Personal of R.H. Gjelsness (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Rudolph H. Gjelsness Memorial Scholarship Fund Speeches [2-40] (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Student evaluations, R.H. Gjelsness' teaching (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - University of Illinois-Bachelor of Science Diploma (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Bound volume of letters to R.H. Gjelsness upon his retirement from the University of Michigan-Filed at back of box 2 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- American Library Association
  - Advisory Committee of the ALA Books for Latin America Project (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Agricultural Libraries Section
    - 1936 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - January-March 1937 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - April-December 1937 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Catalog Section
    - March-June 1930 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - July-September 1930 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - October-December 1930 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - January-March 1931 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - April-May 15,1931 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - May 16-June 1931 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Committee on State Author Headings (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - 54th Annual Conference Proceedings, April 27-28, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - College and Reference Section
    - July 1935-May 1936 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - June 1936-April 1937 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Committee on Cataloging and Classification
    - 1933-1937 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - 1939-1943 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Dewey Decimal Classification
      - 1930-1931 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - January-August 1932 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - September-December 1932 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - January-June 1933 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - July 1933-January 1934 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Committee on Cooperation with Lake Placid Foundation Committee on Decimal Classification, 1933-1936 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Committee on Cooperation with Latin America
    - September-December 1942 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - January 1943 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - February-April 1944 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Bibliographies and Reports (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Cooperative Cataloging
    - 1930-1931 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - 1932 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - 1933-1938 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - International Relations Board
    - July-September 1942 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - October-December 1942 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - January-May 1943 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - June-December 1943 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - 1944 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Library Scholarship & Fellowship Grants, Advisory Group (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Serials Round Table (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Special Membership committee (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Treasurer, 1941-1943 (Box 3, Folder 38)
- American Library Association Catalog Code Revision Committee (Box 4)
  - General
    - 1932-1935 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 1933-1939 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - 1940-1942 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Added entry (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Anonymous Classics I (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Anonymous Classics II (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Anonymous Classics III (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Bible (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Capitalization I (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Capitalization II (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Collation I 14-12] (Box 4)
  - Collation II (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Collation III (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Committee on Use I (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Committee on Use II (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Contents (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Definitions I (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Definitions II (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Definitions III (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Definitions IV (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Definitions V (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Definitions VI (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Definitions VII (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Documents (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Entry I (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Entry II (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Entry III (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Entry IV (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Glossary (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Imprint (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Incunabula (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Index (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Joint Author (Box 4, Folder 33A)
  - Manuscripts I (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Manuscripts II (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Maps (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Music I (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Music II (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Music III (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Personal Authors (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Personal Authors II (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Preface (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Religious Headings I (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Religious Headings II (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Religious Headings III (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Societies and Institutions (Box 4, Folder 46-47)
  - Title entry (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Transcription of title (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Transliteration (Box 4, Folder 50-52)
  - Drafts containing several sections of the Code (Box 4, Folder 53)
- American Library Association Catalog Code Revision Committee
  - Code comments
    - Undated (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
    - May 1940-October 1941 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - November-December 1941 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - January-April 1942 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - May 1-20, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - May 21-June 12, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - June 13, 1942-March 14, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence
    - June 1934-October 1935 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - November-December 1935 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - January-February 1936 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - March 1-19, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - March 20-31, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - April 1-19, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - April 20-30, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - May 1936 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - June 1936 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - July-August 1936 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - September-October 1936 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - November-December 1936 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - January-February 11, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - February 12-March 1937 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - April 1937 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - May 1937 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - June-July 1937 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - August-December 1937 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - January-April 1938 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - May 1938 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - June-July 1938 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - August-December 1938 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - January-May 1939 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - June-December 1939 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - January-July 1940 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - August-December 1940 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - January-May 1941 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - June-September 1941 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - October-December 1941 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - January-July 1942 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - August 1942-December 1943 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - 1944-1946 (Box 5, Folder 41)
- British Library Association-Code Committee
  - 1936 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - 1938 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - 1939-1943 (Box 5, Folder 44)
- Consultants Files
  - Davis and Elkins College (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Enoch Pratt Free Library Reclassification Program (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Oral Roberts University (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Vanderbilt University (Box 6, Folder 3A)
- Foreign Service
  - Baghdad, Iraq
    - Correspondence
      - 1962 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - 1963 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Finances (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Report, with preparatory materials (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Bogotá, Colombia
    - Correspondence
      - March-May 1942 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - June-August 1942 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - September 1942-February 1943 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Finances (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Library Course
      - Course materials [6-14] (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - Lectures (Box 6, Folder 15)
      - Reports (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Committee on International Exchange of Persons (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Denmark-cancelled (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Lima, Peru-Cancelled (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Mexico City, Mexico, Benjamin Franklin Library
    - Bibliographies (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence
      - 1942-1944 (Box 6, Folder 21)
      - 1945-1946 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Planning (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Programs and Exhibitions [6-25] (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Reports (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Mexico City, Mexico-Escuela Nacional de Antropología Library Course
    - General (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Lectures, English version [6-29] (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Mexico City, Mexico Union Catalog Project
    - Policies and Procedures [6-31] (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - New Delhi, India-Projected (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Puerto Rico (Box 6, Folder 33)
- Rudolph H. Gjelsness
  - Manuscripts, unpublished (Box 6, Folder 34-36)
  - Publications (Box 6, Folder 37-38)
  - Translations from the Norwegian
    - Björnsterne Björnson (Box 6, Folder 39-40)
    - Johann Falkberget (Box 6, Folder 41-43)
      - Biographical (Box 6, Folder 44)
      - Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 45)
      - Lisbeth of Jarnfjeld, Reviews of Gjelsness translation (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Johann Ludvig Herberg (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6, Folder 48)
- American Library Association Catalog Code-1960 Revision
  - Author and title entry [7-2] (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Comments (Box 7, Folder 3-8)
  - Proceedings of the Institute on Catalog Code Revision, Montreal, 1960; 5 volumes (Box 7, Folder 9-13)
- International Federation of Library Associations
  - International Conference on Cataloging Principles, Paris, October 1961
    - Comments (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Position Papers (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Reports (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Photographs
  - Family (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Mexico-Biblioteca Benjamin Franklin and others, 1942-1946 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Travel-Norway, 1924-1925 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Travel-Oregon (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Travel-other, and miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - University of Illinois, Class of 1920 and Luther College, honorary degree (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - World War 1 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Unidentified: most probably Oregon. (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - University of Michigan libraries, lantern slides (Box 7, Folder 9)
    (Includes William Warner Bishop photo)
- Albums
  - Travel and family shots (Box 7)
    (camping, hiking, mountains; most unidentified)
  - A.) World War I in Germany, France, circa 1919 (Box 7)
  - B.) "At home," Reynolds, N.D.(3 pages) and Soldiers and other subjects in U.S., particularly San Antonio, Texas, 1918-1919 (Box 7)
  - C.) At or near University of Illinois, Champaign, 1919-1920 (Box 7)
  - France, England, Germany, and U.S., 1917-1923 (Box 7)
    (North and South Dakota, Oregon, University of Illinois, and other).
  - Unidentified travel photos in Europe, the East, the U.S. and Panama., 1920s (Box 7)
  - Unidentified farm and home, and family photos, circa 1900-1915 (Box 7)